Finding Aid for Alexander G. Ruthven Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- President's Office, 1929-1952
  - Photographs
    A small photographs series includes several portraits of Ruthven, photos ceremonial occasions such as commencement exercises, Ruthven posed with regents and other officials, family photos and several pictures of Ruthven with his Morgan horses.
    - Portraits, Family, Ceremonial Occasions, 1 folder (Box 64)
    - Negatives, miscellaneous, including the garden at Preeident's House, 1929-1932 (Box 64)
    - Portraits (Folder UAm)
  - Topical Files, 1931-1935
    The Topical Files, 1931-1935, consist of correspondence and other papers organized by topic. The file, which was transferred to the library in 1984, overlaps in part with the general correspondence files and Subject Files.
    - A-Y, 5 folders (Box 64)
      (primarily correspondence; some overlap with the general correspondence files)
    - Deans and Regents, 23 folders (Box 64)
      (correspondence with)
    - Broadcasting Service (Reports), 1933-1934 (Box 65)
    - Buildings and Grounds, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Carnegie Corporation (Box 65)
    - Clements Library, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Committees (Box 65)
    - Deans (Letters to all), 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Dentistry, School of, 1935 (Box 65)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - Director of Plant Extension (L.M. Gram), 1933 (Box 65)
    - Dormitories, 1933 (Box 65)
    - Early Modern English Dictionary, 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - Education, School of, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Engineering, College of, 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - Entertainment and Research Fund (A.G. Ruthven), 1931-1935 (Box 65)
    - Executive Committee, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Gifts (exclusive of funds for scholarships and fellowships), 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Industrial Relations, 1933-1934 (Box 65)
    - Literature, Science and the Arts, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Lydia Mendelssohn Theatre, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Michigan League, 1933 (Box 65)
    - Middle English Dictionary, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Museums, 1933-1934 (Box 65)
    - Observatory, 1933-1934 (Box 65)
    - Operating Committee, 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - Other Universities, 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - Parke, Davis and Company Herbarium, 1933-1934 (Box 65)
    - Pharmacy, College of, 1933 (Box 65)
    - President's Advisory Committee, 1933-1934 (Box 65)
    - Psychopathic Hospital, 1935 (Box 65)
    - Rackham Fund, 1935 (Box 65)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - R.O.T.C., 1931-1935 (Box 65)
    - Scholarships and Fellowships, 1934 (Box 65)
    - State Board of Vocational Education, 1935 (Box 65)
    - State Building Program, 1933 (Box 65)
    - Summer Session, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
    - Teachers Insurance and Annuity, 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - University Extension, 1935 (Box 65)
    - University Hospital, 1933-1935 (Box 65)
- Academic and Professional
  The Academic and Professional subgroup includes material relating to Ruthven's work as a zoologist and as director of the university's Museum of Zoology and the University Museum. The subgroup is organized into two series: Correspondence and Government Work.
  - Correspondence File
    The Correspondence series, arranged alphabetically by correspondent, covers a range of topics with many distinguished zoologists, reflecting Ruthven's own stature in the field of zoology and also includes much information on the administration of the university museum. Some of the papers predate Ruthven's tenure at the university and are in fact papers maintained by J. B. Steere when he directed the university museum.
    - Adams, Charles C., 1904-1928; 2 folders (Box 51)
      (51-1; 51-2)
    - Allen, Glover M., 1903-1925 (Box 51)
      (51-3)
    - Amaral, Afranio do, 1923-1928 (Box 51)
      (51-4)
    - Andrews, A.W., 1909-1929 (Box 51)
      (51-5)
    - Avinoff, Andre, 1928-1929 (Box 51)
      (51-6)
    - Ahl, Ernst, 1924-1925 (Box 51)
      (51-7)
    - Agassiz, Alexander, 1876-1927 (Box 51)
      (51-8)
    - Bailey, Vernon, 1907-1914 (Box 51)
      (51-9)
    - Baird, Spencer F., 1878-1923 (Box 51)
      (51-10)
    - Barbour, Thomas, 1909-1930 (Box 51)
      (51-10a)
    - Blanchard, Frank N., 1917-1928 (Box 51)
      (51-11)
    - Ba-Bz, 1904-1929 (Box 51)
      (51-12)
    - Creaser, Charles W., 1921-1936 (Box 51)
      (51-13)
    - Ca-Cz, 1906-1939 (Box 51)
      (51-14)
    - Da-Dz, 1906-1928 (Box 51)
      (51-15)
    - Eigenmann, Carl H., 1913-1928 (Box 51)
      (51-16)
    - Ea-Ez, 1921-1932 (Box 51)
      (51-17)
    - Flye, Orlando L., 1913-1930 (Box 51)
      (51-18)
    - Fox, George R., 1914-1927 (Box 51)
      (51-19)
    - Fa-Fz, 1903-1949 (Box 51)
      (51-20)
    - Gaige, Frederick M., 1911-1926 (Box 51)
      (51-21)
    - Ga-Gz, 1899-1930 (Box 51)
      (51-22)
    - Hankinson, Thomas L., 1905-1936 (Box 51)
      (51-24)
    - Hanshaw, Samuel, 1908-1926 (Box 51)
      (51-25)
    - Hubbs, Carl L., 1917-1929 (Box 51)
      (51-26)
    - Ha-Hz, 1912-1936 (Box 51)
      (51-27)
    - Jones, J. Paul, 1922-1929 (Box 51)
      (51-28)
    - Ja-Jz, 1904-1931 (Box 51)
      (51-29)
    - Kelly, Howard A., 1921-1930 (Box 51)
      (51-30)
    - Ka-Kz, 1892-1931 (Box 51)
      (51-31)
    - Ledyard, Edgar M., 1912-1930 (Box 51)
      (51-32)
    - La-Lz, 1903-1929 (Box 51)
      (51-33)
    - Mershon, William B., 1907-1927 (Box 51)
      (51-34)
    - Ma-Mz, 1905-1937 (Box 51)
      (51-35)
    - Netting, M. Graham, 1927-1948 (Box 52)
      (52-1)
    - Newcomb, William W., 1908-1928 (Box 52)
      (52-2)
    - Noble, G. Kingsley, 1915-1927 (Box 52)
      (52-3)
    - Ortenburger, Arthur, 1917-1929 (Box 52)
      (52-4)
    - Pearse, A. S., 1911-1928 (Box 52)
      (52-5)
    - Pa-Pz, 1907-1929 (Box 52)
      (52-6)
    - Ra-Rz, 1902-1953 (Box 52)
      (52-7)
    - Sa-Si, 1906-1931 (Box 52)
      (52-8)
    - Sm-Sz, 1911-1933 (Box 52)
      (52-9)
    - Stejneger, Leonhard, 1903-1931 (Box 52)
      (52-10)
    - Taverner, P.A., 1905-1922 (Box 52)
      (52-11)
    - Ta-Tz, 1912-1923 (Box 52)
      (52-12)
    - Van Denburgh, John, 1904-1924 (Box 52)
      (52-13)
    - Wagner, A.F., 1917-1919 (Box 52)
      (52-14)
    - Walker, Bryant
      - Undated (Box 52)
        (52-15)
      - 1872-1908 (Box 52)
        (52-16)
      - 1909-1911 (Box 52)
        (52-17)
      - 1912-1913 (Box 52)
        (52-18)
      - 1914-1915 (Box 52)
        (52-19)
      - 1916-1917 (Box 52)
        (52-20)
      - 1918-1919 (Box 52)
        (52-21)
      - 1920-1921 (Box 52)
        (52-22)
      - 1922 (Box 52)
        (52-23)
      - 1923 (Box 52)
        (52-24)
      - 1924 (Box 53)
        (53-1)
      - 1925 (Box 53)
        (53-2)
      - 1926 (Box 53)
        (53-3)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 53)
        (53-4)
      - 1929-1930 (Box 53)
        (53-5)
    - Williamson, E. B., 1904-1932 (Box 53)
      (53-6)
    - Wa-Wz, 1904-1929 (Box 53)
      (53-7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence
      - 1907-1908, undated (Box 53)
        (53-8a)
      - 1917 (Box 53)
        (53-8b)
      - 1919
        - Undated and May-August, 1919 (Box 53)
          (53-8c)
        - September-October (Box 53)
          (53-8d)
        - November-December (Box 53)
          (53-8e)
      - January-March 1920 (Box 53)
        (53-8f)
      - 1921-1922 (Box 53)
        (53-8g)
      - 1922 (Box 53)
        (53-8h)
      - 1924 (Box 53)
        (external)
        (53-8i)
      - 1924 (Box 53)
        (university)
        (53-8j)
      - 1925 (Box 53)
        (53-8k)
      - 1927-1929 (Box 53)
        (53-81)
      - 1929-1931 (Box 53)
        (53-8m)
    - Collection of Reptiles in New Mexico and Arizona, 1907 (Box 53)
      (53-9)
    - Loans of specimens, 1907-1921 (Box 53)
      (53-10)
  - State of Michigan
    The State of Michigan series consist of papers relating to Ruthven's work with the state surveys of geological and biological resources 1908-1923) and the Department of Conservation (1924-1929).
    - Geological Survey of Michigan files, 1908-1913 (Box 54)
    - Geological and Biological Survey of Michigan files, 1914-1923 (Box 54)
    - Michigan Department of Conservation files, 1924-1929 (Box 54)